Guide to the Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism, 1536-1996 and undated RL.00413
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Subject Files Series, 1727-1994 and undated, 6 boxes
  Letters, legal and financial documents, portrait and landscape engravings, maps, photographs, research notes, autographs, franks, handbills, and other material that reflect FB's research interests in English and Methodist history of the 18th and 19th centuries. Arranged alphabetically by topic or geographical name.
  - Africa, 1817-1887 and undated, 29 items (Box SU 1)
    Includes portraits of over two dozen missionaries to Africa and various manuscripts about the early history of the mission to Sierra Leone.
    - Portraits--engravings of missionaries, ministers, and other church officials, 1817-1887 and undated, 26 items (Box SU 1)
    - Sierra Leone--mission history, 1812 and 1848, 3 items (Box SU 1)
      Correspondence and other documents on the early history of the Wesleyan Methodist missions in Sierra Leone. In an affidavit of 1812 Jan. 28, a citizen of Freetown swears that "George Warren, Preacher in the Connexion of the late Rev. John Wesley," did not pray, preach, or read in the Connexion's meeting house on a Sunday morning earlier that month. An 1848 letter from Francis Collier to Rev. S.R. Hall recalls events of some forty years earlier, regarding Thomas Coke's appointment of Warren to establish a mission in Sierra Leone. And a petition to the Wesleyan Missions in London, also from 1848 and signed by some seventy preachers and class leaders in Sierra Leone, requests that Thomas Dove be re-appointed as General Superintendent of the Sierra Leone missions.
  - Armed Forces, 1857-1870, 55 items (Box SU 1)
    One printed and illustrated playbill for an evening of "Vocal, Instrumental, and Terpsichorean Entertainment" aboard the H.M.S. Duke of Wellington, 1857 Jan. 1, featuring the Virginia Minstrels, Ethiopian Serenaders, and the Young Patagonian or Morocco Monkey.
    Unrelated to the above, there are forty-nine form letters from Charles Prest, Secretary of Wesleyan Army Committee, to ministers at Wesleyan circuits around England, asking for the number of militiamen their chapels this year (1866). Autograph replies from respondents vary from simple completion of the form to additional notes.
    Soldiers' Home at Aldershot, 1868-1870: four letters from Joseph Webster, thanking various contributors to a fund for a proposed home for soldiers near Aldershot; one letter to the editor from Charles H. Kelly, in support of the same home.
  - Asia, 1813-1873 and undated, 18 items
    Correspondence Series, Thomas Coke Letters
    Volumes Series, Letter Book Simpson D:388 (long letter to his sister from Alfred Levell, India, 1859, about his experiences there)(
    Frank Baker Papers, Subject Files, William Ault (letter from India and Ceylon, 1814)
    - Portraits--engravings of missionaries, ministers, and other church officials, 1813-1873 and undated (Box SU 1)
    - Printed and Visual material -- printed materials re: Methodist missionary activity in Bombay and South India, 1791-1793, 1909, 1939; map and engravings, 1814 and undated., 3 items (Box SU 1)
      Conversion of a Young Man in the East-Indies, 1791-1793: Series of narrative letters from Bombay, printed in several issues of the Arminian Magazine.
      Wesleyan Missionary Newspaper from Madras (now Chennai), 1909, presumably in Tamil language.
      Missionary letter from South India, 1939, detailing work there.
      Engravings of a mission in Colombo.
      Map of Ceylon (Sri Lanka) showing the locations of Methodist Missions.
  - Australasia, 1851-1887 and undated, 54 items
    Volumes Series, Letter Book Simpson D:391: letter from W. Lowry, Auckland, 1844, about the mission to New Zealand
    - Document: "Instructions to Walter Lawry General Superintendent of the Wesleyan Missions in New Zealand, the Friendly Island and Feejee [Fiji]," 1851 (Box SU 1)
      FB note: "copy of document in the handwriting of Dr. Osborn, probable date 1851 or thereabouts"
    - Hunt, John and Joseph, 1838, 1853, and undated, 4 items (Box SU 1)
      Materials related to the Wesleyan missionary John Hunt (1812-1848) and his brother Joseph. Contents: letter from J. Hunt, 1838 Apr. 21; engraving, "Illustrated Map of Feejee, Presented by the Missionary Committee to Collectors of Juvenile Christmas Offerings, 1853," showing images of many sites in Fiji, including the tomb of the Rev. John Hunt; clipping on John Hunt (obituary or memoir); engraving of Joseph Hunt.
    - Portraits--engravings of missionaries, ministers, and other church officials, 1855-1887 and undated, 37 items (Box SU 1)
    - Visual materials: engravings of missions in New Zealand and Feejee (Fiji), undated, 2 items (Box SU 1)
    - Visual materials: letter and engravings (b/w and color) by George Baxter of missionary scenes and people in Fiji, New Zealand, Madras, Ceylon, 1844 and undated, 10 items (Box SU 1)
      Contents: Baxter correspondence to Jabez Bunting about the first image, 1844 Nov. 18; Untitled engraving (color, 9x12), John Waterhouse landing at Fiji (mislabled in pencil, verso, as Rev. L. Williams); "Va-Ta-Ah, the Feejeean Princess" (color); two engravings (color) of Wesleyan chapels and mission houses in New Zealand and Madras; and five engravings of ships, including three of the missionary ship "John Wesley" and one entitle "Destruction of the 'Tanjore' by Lightning off Ceylon." A penciled note on the last item says "Dr. [Elijah] Hoole in the boat holding up his hand." Found separately, a copy of FB's extended note about the history and provenance of the large engraving in included in the folder. He identifies subject as "John Waterhouse, appointed 1839, as 'General Superintendent of the Wesleyan Missions in Australia and Polynesia.'"
  - Autographs: C.19 letters, Methodist, 1810-1840, 20-30 items (Box SU 1)
    Miscellaneous autographs on title pages, endpapers, and other fragments. 2 folders from CORR1, plus 1 folder from Smith
  - Baptismal Certificates, 1787, 1818, 1826, 1883, 1952-3, 12 items (Box SU 1)
    Contains the following original and reproductions of baptismal certificates: 1787 photograph of John Wesley autograph; 1826 photograph with FB correspondence dated 1952-3 documenting provenance; 1883 original. Attached to the 1883 item is a note documenting a 1798 certificate not found.
    RELATED MATERIAL: See also Correspondence Series, Adam Clarke Papers.
  - Bibliography--other scholars' notes on Wesleys' publications, 1830s, 1913-1919, 1944-1945, and undated, 2 folders (Box SU 1)
    Folder 1 houses manuscript notes of Rev. S. R. Hall, a 19th-century Wesleyan Methodist minister, passed to FB by Bretherton in the 1940s. Undated text with 1831 watermarks. Folder 2 contains correspondence, notes, and writings of John Simon, John Telford, and other scholars, 1913-1919 and undated, about editions of JW's sermons.
  - Book plates and miscellaneous items, 1775-1936 and undated, 3 folders, 90 items (Box SU 1)
    Mainly a collection of 18th and 19th century British Methodist book plates. Found in the box with the book plates were miscellaneous items, including 2 postcard advertisements for Sugden's Flour, a small color portrait of Sir Christopher Wren, invitations to various services, a Memorial Book for Mary Hannah,and various other items.
  - Burnley history, 1833-1870, 1912, 1917, 1961, and undated, 20 items (Box SU 1)
    Correspondence, notes, account pages, cards, clippings, and 1833-1834 class schedule, all related to Burnley Circuit and the Wesleyan chapel there. Also included here are two small volumes, a journal of the Wesleyan chapel in Burnley, 1839-1870, and a log of School's Collections, 1852-1862.
    RELATED MATERIAL: See also the two Burnley account books and journals, housed in the Volumes Series.
  - Canada, 1802-1877 and undated, 24 items (Box SU 2)
    - Correspondence, 1838
      - Lusher, R. L., Montreal, to John Shum, Bath, 1838 Jan. 5 (Box SU 2)
        Long and detailed letter from R. L. (Robert Langham) Lusher (1787-1849), writing from Montreal, where he had recently returned from Bath after a previous mission in Canada in the 1820s. In reporting to Shum he gives many details about the current political, an important era in Canadian history that came to be known as the Upper and Lower Canada Rebellion of 1837.
    - Portraits--engravings of Canadian missionaries, ministers, and other church officials, 1802-1877 and undated, 23 items (Box SU 2)
  - Caribbean and Latin America, 1780-1878 and undated, 15 items
    Various items in different subseries of the Printed Materials Series, including The Late Insurrection in Demarara, and Riot in Barbadoes, 1824; Dreadful Hurricane in the West Indies, 1819; and Wesleyan Missions in the West Indies, 1825
    Volumes Series, Letter Book Simpson E:292 (long letter from Wilkinson, Belize, Honduras, 1826 Jan. 13 about the mission there)
    William Smith Papers, 1785-1860: correspondence and documents about the 1823 riot in Barbadoes referenced above
    Frank Baker Papers, Subject Files, "Gilbert Family" and "West Indies" files: research on early missionaries in the West Indies
    Monographs on Methodism and the West Indies: the Rubenstein Library's Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism holds several monographs on these topics--see especially items by or about Thomas Coke
    - Portraits: engravings of missionaries, ministers, and other church officials, 1787-1878 and undated, 13 items (Box SU 2)
    - Printed material: A Private Letter from Jamaica, 1780 Aug. 2 (Box SU 2)
      Letter of four pages from an unidentified book or serial that describes life and conditions in Jamaica. Portrays the terrible life of the slaves, concluding that only one class of people suffer more--"our fair countrywomen."
  - Conferences, 1804-1978 and undated
    Manuscript and printed minutes, notes, and other materials from various Wesleyan Methodist Conferences.
    - Conferences--1804, 1855-1880, 1927-1960, 1978, and undated (Box SU 2)
      Eleven Wesleyan Methodist Conference Admission Cards, circa 1855-1880, for Rev. Francis Barker. Autographs for presidents of corresponding years present. Nine admission tickets, circa 1930-1959. FB research and notes on Wesleyan Methodist Conferences, mid-20th cent. Copy of a document, circa 1804, by John Pawson: "Thoughts Respecting the Conference". Transcribed by A. Rowlinson. An unbound article from the Wesleyan Methodist Magazine, circa 1863: "The Early Methodist Conferences". A page from an 1859/60 copy of The Watchman and Wesleyan Advertiser. One photograph, "A Key to Methodism in 1866," undated. One engraving, "The First Wesleyan Conference 1744," undated but probably 19th century. One photograph(?), "Key to Groupe (sic), Commemorative of First Wesleyan Mixed Conference Held in Bradford, August, 1878". Various 20th cent. newspaper clippings.
    - Conferences--minutes, 1910-1915, 1924 (Box SU 2)
      Manuscript and printed minutes and notes of various Wesleyan Methodist conferences held in London, Bristol, and elsewhere.
    - Printed material, various conferences, 1876, 1927 (Box SU 2)
  - Dissenters, 1770 (Box SU 2)
    "Licence for Rochdale [Lancaster] Methodist preaching House," 1770 Jan. 5. Contemporary copy.
  - Education, 1844-1879 and undated, 8 items (Box SU 2)
    Correspondence and certificates regarding various contributions to the Education Fund. Unrelated to these items, the Education folder also contains the pamphlet Subscriptions of Travelling Preachers Towards the Purchase of Woodhouse-Grove School, undated [early/mid-19 century); this items lists the names, stations, and contributions of some 700 preachers.
    RELATED MATERIAL: Many other letters on the Education Fund can be found in the Correspondence Series, Methodist Preachers Subseries.
  - Franks (by various individuals), 1800-1830s, approx. 45 items (Box SU 2)
  - History of Medicine, 1792-1812, 1854, 1903, 1938, 1964, and undated, 5 folders
    Receipts (bills), receipts (recipes and remedies), materials about JW's interest in medicine and home remedies, and correspondence and case histories of three well-known doctors in 18th and 19th century England: Andrew Duncan, the elder (1744-1828); John Coakley Lettsom (1744-1815); and Sir Walter Farquhar, (1738-1819). In addition to materials in the box list below, other Baker materials on the history of medicine can be found elsewhere in this or other collections in the Rubenstein Library.
    Robert Farquhar Letter Book and Journal, 1775-1819 (Volumes Series, Writings and Addresses): correspondence from 18th century physicians
    Elizabeth (Ritchie) Mortimer Letters, 1779-1836 (Correspondence Series): descriptions of illnesses and cures, including JW's interest in electro therapy
    Sarah Crosby Papers, 1760-1804: recipes for "stomachic pills" and "aperient pills"
    Duncan, Andrew, Cases (manuscript records) Nov. 7th, 1776-May 27, 1777; April 3d, 1777-July 9th, 1777: case histories of 18th century doctors (Rubenstein Library, History of Medicine Bound Manuscripts, gift of FB, 1980)
    Frank Baker Papers, Subject Files, Medicine (JW and Methodists): general research on this topic and detailed description of Andrew Duncan gift, above
    Monographs on JW and medicine: the Rubenstein Library's Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism and History of Medicine collections hold several dozen monographs by or about JW on medical topics
    - Dallinger, W.H. (1842-1909), 1878-1894 and undated (Box SU 2)
      One letter, a portrait, clippings, and an interview with Dallenger (1842-1909), Wesleyan Methodist minister and micro-biologist. A copy of "The Young Man," circa 1894. Interview entitled: The Religion of a Scientist: an Interview with the Rev. W. H. Dallinger, D.D., D.Sc., F.R.S., 1894.
    - Correspondence--letters to Dr. John Lettsom, 1792-1812, 1964, and undated, 7 items (Box SU 2)
      Five letters from three physicians and a minister to Dr. John Lettsom (1744-1815), physician, philanthropist, and one of the founders of Medical Society of London. Two letters from Jonathan Stokes, 1792 and 1812, discuss new medical literature, including the Botanical Arrangement and new papers by a Dr. Pearce of Philadelphia. Dr. Vaughn of Leicester (1793), writes to Lettsom about a new disease which, in his experience, kills within 86 hours, and one of the symptoms of which are spasms of the diaphragm unlike any that occur with other known diseases; he posits that this is a disorder of the nervous system as opposed to one resulting from the circulatory fluids, and discusses some experimental treatments. Rev. John Rudd, Preston, writes to Dr. Lettsom in 1811, claiming that an instrument exists, housed in some of the country's palaces, which can revive persons apparently dead; he also mentions the Royal Humane Society, an organization formed in 1774 aimed at reanimating the dead, esp. those who died by drowning; he also refers Dr. Lettsom to others who know more about it and might be able to help further.
    - "Mr. Barrowclough--Dr. to John Halkyard"--one manuscript receipt for medical supplies with circa 60 entries, by day, from 1804 Mar. 28-Sept. 16 (Box SU 2)
    - Receipts and remedies, undated (Box SU 2)
      Book cover has written on it two hand-written medicinal remedies, "A Receipt to Cure the [indistinguishable] Watter" and "For the Same Desorder[...]". Probably late-18th or early 19th century.
    - Turrell, W. J., John Wesley: Physician & Electrotherapist, Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1938. 38 pp. (Box SU 2)
      Also includes signed letter from Turrell, a physician and author of other books on electrotherapy; and notes by FB on the history of JW's interest in electricity and electrotherapy.
    - Printed Materials (Box SU 2)
      Preface to "Circle of the Sciences" (?), 1854. One folio.
      "Winter Medicine Chest," information on liquorice as a medicine, undated. One page.
      Typewritten notes from the formation of the Sheffield Microscopical Society. 2 pages.
      Eight pages from "The Chemist and Druggist" 1903, including articles and advertisements.
  - Lincolnshire
    RELATED MATERIAL: See also Volumes Series, Local Histories Subseries.
    - Clippings, 1884-1925 (Box SU 2)
      Clippings from Grantham Journal, Methodist Reader, and other sources about events in Lincolnshire.
    - Correspondence, Riggall--research requests and other inquiries, 1924-1925 (Box SU 2)
    - Correspondence, FB--1951-1958 (Box SU 2)
    - Photographs of Alford and Lincolnshire preachers, circa 1841-1875, and of Hogsthorpe Wesleyan Chapel, undated, approx. 20 items (Box SU 2)
    - Research--manuscripts: Barduey Methodism: a Brief History, by Rev. H. Osborne Annett, 1938 (Box SU 3)
    - Research--manuscripts: Sketch of Wesleyan Methodism at Fulletby, 1878 (Box SU 3)
    - Research--transcriptions: Grimsby Circuit Records, 1784-1785 (Box SU 3)
    - Research notes, 1865-1965, 8? folders (Box SU 3)
      Includes notes, printed materials, and transcriptions--mainly by Riggall, supplemented by FB--on various topics, including "line-dissenters," lists of ministers and members, and a copy of The Victoria History of the County of Lincoln, Vol. 2, edited by William Page, F.S.A., 1906
    - Lincolnshire obituaries extracted by M. Riggall from Methodist Magazine, 1814, 1816, and 1825; and from Wesleyan Methodist Magazine, 1858-1859, 1866, 6 volumes (Box SU 3)
  - Liverpool, 1805-1819, 1861-1902, and undated, 1 of 5 folders, 40 items (Box SU 3)
    Correspondence, manuscript notes, scrapbooks, printed materials, and six early-19th century class schedules from the Liverpool area. Some materials are fragile.
  - Liverpool, 1805-1819, 1861-1902, and undated, 2-4 of 5 folders, 40 items (Box SU 4)
  - Lotteries, 1763-1788, 1934-1963, and undated, 17 items (Box SU 4)
    Variety of notes, printed materials, and engravings on the subject of lotteries. 18th century original materials include printed items on both English and Irish lottery tickets, an order for 50 tickets in 1747 (written and signed by the Bp. of London, a portrait of whom is also included), undated small engravings, and the engraving, "The Representation of the Drawing of the State-Lottery at Guildhall, 1763." Also included, a satirical cartoon series, Gretna Green, or, The Elopement (in reference to the Scottish town on the English border).
  - Manchester history, 1792, 1815, 1826-1829, 3 folders, 11 items (Box SU 4)
    Minutes from five district meetings held in Manchester. Folder 1 contains various loose pages removed from the four pamphlets of the same dates to be found in Folder 2. All items appear to be original autograph minutes except for the pages from 1792, which are labeled as copies. Folder 3 contains printed items from various Manchester chapels, including music to be performed at various services, 1792, 1794, and 1826.
    RELATED MATERIAL: for other items about Manchester local history, see Volumes Series, Local Histories, Manchester.
  - Marriage (Box SU 4)
    One manuscript item circa 1859 and two print items circa 1833 and 1898.
  - Manuscripts--fragments and unidentified items (Box SU 4)
  - Methodist portraits, 1872-1994 and undated, 2 folders and 3 envelopes (Box SU 4)
    FB's correspondence and research related to Methodist portrait engravings. Materials include his index of his collection of engravings, a list of approximately 2000 18th and 19th century preachers. Also contains dealers' listings dating to the 1870s, and three notebook indexes apparently compiled by F. F. Bretherton in the early 1900s and passed on to FB.
    RELATED MATERIAL: FB's collection of portrait engravings is housed in the Visual Materials Series, mainly in the People Subseries and Magazines Subseries.
  - Methodist seat rent tickets, 1782-1840 and undated, 8 items (Box SU 5)
    Eight seat rent tickets from the 18th and 19th century, together with text from FB explaining the history of these items; some items mounted, possibly for an unspecified exhibit or class.
  - Missions and Missionary Societies
    - Missions and Missionary Societies, 1846-47, 1905-08, and undated, 8 items (Box SU 5)
      Three cheques (?), 1846-47, overwritten.
      Two printed Plans for "Services and Meetings for the Banbury Circuit" re: Foreign Missions, 1905-6 (8 pages, stapled) and 1906-7 (tri-fold pamphlet).
      Printed advertisement for "The Missionary Echo," 1908.
      Manuscript sample of "the long-winded resolutions proposed and seconded at Wesleyan F[oreign] M[issions] Meetings a generation ago" (FB note).
      Single loose page with a list of items (not present), including "An address at the formation of a Missionary Society in London by Dr. A. Clarke, Dec. 1, 1814."
    - Wesleyan Methodist Missionary Society, Centenary Celebration, 1913, circa 12 items (Box SU 5)
      Printed materials relating to the Centenary Celebration of the Methodist Missionary Society, 1913.
  - Money and lending, 1776-1976 and undated
    - Lending--One manuscript item circa 1838 and one print item circa 1877 (Box SU 5)
      Manuscript item (1838) is a paper packet entitled "Anecdotes [concerning] The Rev John Wesley". Print item (1877) is entitled "John Wesley and Usury."
    - Money, 1776-1976, circa 30 items (Box SU 5)
      Contents include: currency, certificates, manuscript (original and transcribed) and printed material. Includes American Revolution era currency.
  - Music, 1742 and undated, 2 folders
    - Hymns--artifact, manuscript photocopies, and notes, undated (Box SU 5)
      Artifact is the cover to a hymnal, containing inscription: "Joseph Steel is my name". Photocopies are of 18th century hymns originally bound into this book. Notes by FB explain that the hymns were copies rather than originals, and how and why he disbound the volume, but not the location of disbound hymns.
    - Music--printed music and other print items, 1742 and undated, 12 items (Box SU 5)
      Sheet of printed music, 1742, entitled "Tunes Usually Sung at the Baptist"; sheet of printed music, 18th or 19th century; "Hymn Sheet: for use in Holiness and Christian Workers' Meetings," [pencil note: "in use during [eighteen?] eighties and nineties"]; other printed hymns and bookmark, 19th or early 20th century; and hymns by John Beaumont.
  - Preachers, 1840-1853, 1910, 3 folders
    - Lay preachers--ALS from President and Secretary of the Quarterly Meeting of the Primitive Methodist Connexion, circa 1849 (Box SU 5)
    - Local preachers--notebook and certificate, circa 1840 and 1910 (Box SU 5)
      A printed certificate of membership for the Wesleyan Methodist Local Preachers' Mutual Aid Association. The notebook: A Local Preachers' Mutual Aid. "Bro. Spencers Contributions Book"; "The Wesleyan Local Preacher's Fund in the Seven Oaks Circuit."
    - Preachers' wives and families--print item, "A Preacher's Fund," circa 1853 (Box SU 5)
  - Preaching licences: James and William Fowler, 1797-1798, 1960, and undated, 5 items (Box SU 5)
    Two autograph fragments, signed by James Fowler. One copy of an Ordination Certificate written and signed by Bishop Thomas Coke in 1798 for William Fowler. One print form certifying William Fowler as having taken the requisite oath as a dissenting minister, signed by Henry Selby.
  - Primitive Methodism, 1836-1920, 1950-1960, and undated, 3 folders
    - Correspondence, notes, and clippings, 1840-1863, 1950, and undated, 14 items (Box SU 5)
      Items found tipped or laid in to a A History of the Primitive Methodist Connexion from Its Origins to the Conference of 1860, by John Petty, 1864.
    - Manuscript items and artifacts, circa 1836-1883, 1907-8, 1920, and undated (Box SU 5)